<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The envious man's character a sermon preached at S. Mary's Church in Cambridge / by William Aspin ...</title>
            <author>Aspin, William, 1635 or 6-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13061281</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13061281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97026</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97026)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 406:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The envious man's character a sermon preached at S. Mary's Church in Cambridge / by William Aspin ...</title>
                  <author>Aspin, William, 1635 or 6-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.W. for Ralph Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Envy --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97026:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97026:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The Envious Man's Character.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at S. <hi>MARY</hi>'s CHURCH IN CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM ASPIN,</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Emberton</hi> in <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. W.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Piazza</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97026:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97026:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <p>HAVING ſeriouſly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what might be the reaſon of thoſe heats and immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which do but too viſibly diſturb the quiet of this Church and State, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently found how great a ſhare Envy had in cauſing them. And therefore being to preach a Sermon, <hi>Ad Populum,</hi> in S. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Church in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I thought I could not do better ſervice to Religion, than by endeavouring to detect and diſplay that monſtrous Vice. For 'tis apparent to him that ſees any thing, how great a cauſe it has been of former commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as alſo of our preſent Diſcontents and Diſturbances. I do not wonder, when I
<pb facs="tcp:97026:3"/> hear the greateſt worth defamed, Men of the profoundeſt Wiſdom, and moſt exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Piety and Vertue, either in Church or State, evil ſpoken of. For alas! the eyes of ſome will ever be diſturbed at ſo great a luſtre. The <hi>Iſraelites envied</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes in the Camp, and Aaron the Saint of the Lord. Tertullian</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, the Goſpel muſt needs be a precious thing, becauſe <hi>Nero</hi> hated it. And it plainly argues, that there's ſomething ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent belonging to that man who is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied. And therefore <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ut umbra nuſquam eſt, niſi cum adeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Vit. Sanct. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymi.</note> 
               <hi>lumen: ita celebritas ſanctiſſimi viri non caret invidiâ:</hi> As the ſhadow is never ſeen to appear, but with a lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Body: ſo the fame of the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Perſon, is ſure to be attended with Envy. Hence ſome of the braveſt men that ever the World had, have met with
<pb facs="tcp:97026:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the unkindeſt uſage in it. The reaſon is, becauſe the higher their worth has raiſed them, the fairer mark they have appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Envy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayes, He was not envied in his Minority, becauſe then he had done nothing that was famous and extraordinary. And no ſooner were the <hi>Athenian</hi> Captains by their excellent Conduct, Valour, and Succeſſes, raiſed the higheſt in the eſteem of thoſe over whom they were Victors, but they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently envied and proſcribed by their own Country men. And amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> the renowned <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Fall was owing to the Envy, as well as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of <hi>Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſius;</hi> which <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> himſelf ſaw he was in danger of; when as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us in the Life of <hi>Brutus,</hi> he ſaid, He was not afraid of
<pb facs="tcp:97026:4"/> fat Men, but of lean whitely faced-fellows, meaning thereby <hi>Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> who were ſuch; The thinneſs of their Bodies, and paleneſs of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſcovering the Envy and Malice that was in their hearts. And therefore 'tis a great piece of folly to think the worſe of any one for being envied and evil ſpoken of, becauſe 'tis ſure, the Wiſeſt and beſt men in a Nation, though others may, ſhall not eſcape Cenſure. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly every Chriſtian man's wiſdom to hold on in a ſteady courſe of duty, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to approve himſelf to God in all caſes, not to value much what men think or ſay of him, and to look for his reward in another World, and not in this.</p>
            <p>When I preached it, I had no thought of making this Sermon publick. But ſince that time, which is now about a
<pb facs="tcp:97026:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> year and half, ſomething having happened which I foreſaw might occaſion its co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming abroad, at ſome time or other, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge, I concluded it to be the prudenteſt way to put it out my ſelf, ſince by that means I might avoid ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences which might have happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by anothers doing it. It may be ſome will not like it; becauſe 'tis but too true a Character of themſelves: But that I cannot help. If it ſhall contribute any thing to the quiet, and welfare of the Community, for which it is deſigned, or to the advantage of any individual in it: I ſhall not repent me of what I have now done, being contented to be cenſured by ſome, if I may but profit any.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97026:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97026:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ECCLES. IV. iv.</bibl>
               <q>I conſidered—every right work, that for this a man is envied of his Neighbour.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TWould be matter of juſt wonder and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to a conſidering mind, that Men who are bound to one another by ſo many obligations of Nature, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Intereſt, ſhould yet be at ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h enmity amongſt themſelves, if we were not by infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Revelation acquainted with the degeneracy of our Natures, as the cauſe of it. For ſince there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and agreement between even the Beaſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the ſame kind; it cannot be imagined that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature ſhould be at ſuch odds and diſcords with it ſelf, but that its propenſions are by ſin changed, and but that it ſelf is ſunk below tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Beaſts that periſh. Though indeed, reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſelf, if it had wanted the aſſiſtance of Divine Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ation, might have gone a great way towards thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſcovery, ſince a change in the Effects, muſt of neceſſity argue one in the Cauſe, from whence they proceeded. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wiſeſt Heathen, though they were never able to aſſign the true Cauſe of the degeneracy of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that being beyond their ſearch, and paſt their finding out; yet they eaſily diſcerned that Man's na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was corrupted, and changed from what it ſhould be. Hence in <hi>Horace,</hi> The Soldier is diſpleaſed with his own Profeſſion, and wiſhes himſelf a Merchant;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97026:6"/> The Merchant diſlikes his own Calling, and envies that of the Soldiers. The Lawyer envies the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's happineſs: And the Husbandman is diſpleaſed with his own Calling, and thinks they are only hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that dwell in Cities. What's the reaſon men ſhould find their own conditions ſo uneaſie, and ſhould envy that of other mens? 'Tis not becauſe other mens (all things conſidered) are better for them than their own; For he that makes a change, finds himſelf to be as uneaſie as he was before. And indeed, the ſame Suit is not fit for every ones back: But 'tis becauſe men have not a right apprehenſion of things, and becauſe they would engroſs all the goods of the World to themſelves. And therefore are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled when they ſee any body elſe poſſeſſed of them. 'Tis becauſe their natures are degenerated and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. But whatever be the more general and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, or the more particular, and immediate Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or thing it ſelf, is too obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to eſcape any ones notice, That there is a great deal of Envy in the World, which <hi>Solomon</hi> has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in theſe words, ſaying, <hi>I conſidered—every right work, that for this a man is envied of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Envy ſeems to be the ſame which the Orator <hi>Cicero</hi> has defined it, namely, A grief conceived in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aegritudo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi ex alterius rebus ſecundis ſuſcepta, quae praeſertim nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam jacturam afferunt invidenti.</hi> 4. Tuſe.</note> the mind, at the good which another enjoyes, and that good eſpecially, by which the envious man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives no injury. We'll conſider briefly the parts of this Deſcription, that we may the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97026:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. I ſay, Envy is a grief; and beſides that, every <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Plut. Mor.</hi>
               </note> one who has experienced it, has felt it to be ſo: this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by its effects, it making men ſad and full of complaints that are infeſted with it; It changes the natural pleaſantneſs of the countenance, waſts the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zenoph. Memor. Lib.</hi> 3.</note> Body, and diſquiets the mind. And therefore <hi>David</hi> tells us, <hi>When he was envious at the fooliſh,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 3, 21.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing the proſperity of the wicked, his heart was grieved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis a grief, conceived in the mind, by which <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Plut. de Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia &amp; Odio.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ibid. Pſal. 38. 20.</note> terms 'tis diſtinguiſhed from that grief which Beaſts may have, becauſe of ſome preſent bodily pain, that they are afflicted with, who though they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of grieving, being of a ſenſible nature; Yet they cannot envy one another, becauſe they can have no imagination of the proſperity that others enjoy above themſelves. 'Tis a grief conceived in the mind (at anothers good) and hereby 'tis diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd from hatred, which has for its object evil. 'Tis true, a man may be hated for doing good, as 'twas <hi>David</hi>'s lot, but then 'tis looked upon under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Evil. But Envy has good for its object, not our own, which would excite our joy, but anothers which cauſes our Envy. And <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>'Tis not for any evil, but for good. For every right work, a man is envied of his Neighbour.</hi> That is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For every right work of Art. Thus when a Mechanick has finiſhed a piece of work, according to the rules of his Art, he is envied for it by ſome or other, that are of the ſame Trade with himſelf. And therefore ſuch can ſeldom ſpeak well of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97026:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> but will be ſecretly undermining, and take all occaſions to diſparage and detract from one anothers skill, and love to be finding fault with that which they did not do themſelves. Which was an obſervation long ſince made by the <hi>Greek</hi> Poet; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and is grown into a Proverb amongſt our ſelves. Hence we are told by the Moraliſt, <hi>That all excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is attended with Envy.</hi> A man cannot hope to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in any thing, but he ſhall be envied by ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for it. And 'tis a common Proverb amongſt the <hi>Rabbies, That every Artificer hates the Children of his own Craft.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A man ſhall be envied of his Neighbour for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry right work of Nature.</hi> Such I account are all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural perfections either of mind or Body: As are Wit, Beauty, Strength, or the like. They who have either any or all of theſe, are in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing envied by ſome that want them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For every right work of Grace.</hi> For if a man live uprightly, and do juſtly, in all probability he is like to be a conſiderable gainer by it in this World; though fools are apt to think otherwiſe, 'tis the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt means to advance both his Reputation and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which men that have the greateſt Dealings in the World, ſeem to be convinced of, in that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it, and would be thought to be moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, even then when they have deſigned to ſteer a quite contrary courſe. But it matters not much what ſuch mens thoughts are, ſince we are ſure, that Grace or Godlineſs has the promiſe of the things of this life, and that he who by the conſtant tenor of an upright life, beſt acquits himſelf of his duty to God and Man,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97026:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall ordinarily be beſt accepted of by both. I ſay, ordinarily, becauſe moſt aſſuredly God will value him the more for it; And ſo, unleſs it be very rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, will men too. And he that has the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of God's favour and man's, is moſt likely to advance in his worldly Eſtate, and to become the object of his Neighbour's Envy. Thus likewiſe, if a man by his honeſt Induſtry; thrive and increaſe in Wealth, or if by the merit of his vertues, he be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to honour, he ſhall be envied by ſome body or other. It may be, to ſpeak ſtrictly, no man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied for his grace or goodneſs, but for the rewards of it. For a man may be as holy, and as vertuous as he will, and yet no body will envy him for that; unleſs from thence he be more eſteemed, and be better thought of, or unleſs by ſuch a courſe he thrives in his worldly eſtate, then he ſhall be envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But becauſe 'tis hard to ſeparate between ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and its reward, therefore I may not improperly ſay, That for every right work of grace, <hi>a man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied of his Neighbour.</hi> And thus you ſee anothers good is the object of Envy; or the good which ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther injoyes, is that which cauſes his Neighbour to look upon him with an evil eye. Which is the third Particular to be conſidered in the definition which I have given you of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis for that good eſpecially that a man is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied, by which the envious perſon receives no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. For if one poſſeſſes a good by which another is injured, it makes him hated rather than envied, becauſe he came by it by evil and indirect means; that is, by injuring of another. But what injury can it be to an Artificer, to have another to perfect a more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97026:8"/> curious piece of Work than he? It may accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a loſs to him, becauſe moſt will make uſe of him that's beſt skilled in his Art; but injury it can be none. And what wrong is it to me, if another <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sim ipſe foelix, ſint alii foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciores, non equidem invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo, mihi nihil detrahetur.</hi> Cumberland de Legibus Naturae. p. 128. A ſaying like that excellent Author.</note> be wittier, handſomer, and ſtronger than I? I have never the leſs of either, becauſe he has more. That degree which he has above me, was not taken from me: And ſo, if he excell me in any vertue; or, as a reward of that vertue, if he be better thought of, find greater favour, and be preferred before me, 'tis but as it ſhould be. He has what he deſerves, and I am not injured by it. For, though he have more than I, yet I may not have leſs, but more than I deſerve. Thus you ſee the object of Envy, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good. A man is envied for any good of Art, of Nature, and of Grace too. For the higheſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, goodneſs and innocence, is no fence againſt it, as is plain, becauſe our bleſſed Saviour himſelf, for Envy, was delivered over to be proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the Civil Magiſtrate. Nay, as <hi>Syneſius</hi> has <note place="margin">de Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> obſerved, Envy is not ſo much ſuppreſſed by vertue, as inflamed, or not ſo much appeaſed, as inraged. Neither can that good, which is poſſeſſed without the wrong of any one, ſecure a man from it; that good of another being eſpecially the object of it, by which the envious perſon receives no injury. Thus having ſhewed you the monſtrous nature of Envy, our next enquiry ſhall be into the Cauſes of it. And as we commonly gueſs from the ſordid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a man's temper, at that of his Birth and Breeding; ſo doubtleſs, this more than Brutiſh vice of Envy muſt needs be of very baſe extraction and original, whither if we trace it, we ſhall find it deſcended from one, or all of theſe Cauſes. And,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97026:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. From Ignorance. For if the envious man did not think ſome things to be valuable beyond what really they are, ſuch as Riches, and Honour, Beauty, Wit, and the like, he would not grieve to ſee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſeſſed of them. Alas! a man may enjoy all theſe to his hurt, and 'tis but too evident, that a great many do, all indeed that miſ-imploy them, and uſe them to other ends, than thoſe for which God deſigned them. And then, if we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood things aright, they'd be the objects of our pity, rather than of our envy, as being more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than others that want them. Our Saviour oppoſes the Goods of Fortune to the Goods of Grace, calling the Goods of Grace <hi>true riches;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 11.</note> thereby implying, That the Goods of Fortune are falſe riches. And indeed, in the event, they are as often evils as goods. And ſurely, none would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy the goods of Grace which any one poſſeſſes, if he underſtood that they were imparted to him for the advantage of others, as well as his that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them, and conſequently, that others may be benefited by them if they will. Methinks it ſhould rejoice us to ſee that man rich, that's obliged to maintain us out of what he has. This I ſay upon ſuppoſition, that the goods of Grace may be ſaid properly to be envied. But that envy is owing to ignorance, we need no other proof than what <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> will furniſh us with, who when he hath told us, <hi>That he envied the proſperity of the wicked,</hi> and <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> was grieved at the Goods which they injoyed, he afterwards lets us know the cauſe of that envy in him, ſaying, <hi>So fooliſh was I and ignorant.</hi> And <note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> therefore, when once he underſtood things aright,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97026:9"/> he's ſo far from envying them any longer, that he deſcribes them as objects of the greateſt <note place="margin">Verſ. 18, 19, 20.</note> pity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Unbelief, is another cauſe of Envy. For he that believes God is All-ſufficient, and has enough of all Goods to beſtow upon every man, and that every gift of his is the iſſue of his infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs, will never grieve to ſee ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man poſſeſſed of it. As that Child who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves his Father has enough left for him, and that he has done well in the diſpoſal of part of his Eſtate upon his Brethren, will never be troubled at it. The elder Brother in the Parable would not have been diſturbed at the proviſion which his Father made for his younger Brother's welcome home, but that he thought what was ſpent that way, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonged to him, and that his Father did ill in beſtowing it upon another. And therefore we read, That they <hi>who were moved with envy, were the Jews which believed not.</hi> He that firmly believes <note place="margin">Act. 17. 5.</note> that God in infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, allots to every man his portion here, and what's beſt for him as he moſt certainly does, all things conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as he'll ſee no reaſon he has to grieve that he has leſs than another: ſo he'll ſee no cauſe he has to envy another man that has more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Pride is another cauſe of Envy. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good another poſſeſſes, the proud man, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a great opinion of his own merit, thinks it properly belongs to him. And hence he's griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee another enjoy that which he accounts his own due. Envy ever accompanies Pride.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97026:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> And therefore the proudeſt perſons are the moſt envious, as was evident in the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and is but too apparent in thoſe whoſe Principles and Practices argue them to be deſcended from them. They that fancy themſelves to be more holy than all others, can hardly be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that any others ſhould injoy what they account good but themſelves And therefore they would have all Temporal Power and Jurisdiction, and would exclude all others, as carnal and formal, from having any thing to do with the regiment of the World. They would diſpoſe of Crowns and Scepters, imagining that a right to Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is founded in Grace, and that Grace is no where to be found but amongſt themſelves. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this opinion to be found only amongſt a few, from whoſe weak and crazy heads, one can ſcarce expect much better reaſoning; But 'tis become the avowed Doctrine of a whole Church, whoſe reaſon would ſoon detect the Error, if Pride and Intereſt, did not obſtruct the diſcovery of it. Hence they tell us, That the Pope has power to deprive that Prince of his Kingdom, and to depoſe him from his Government, that deſerts the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, and refuſes obedience to the Apoſtolick See, <note place="margin">Binii Concil. de Haereticis.</note> as is declared in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council held under <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>But ſince God gives theſe outward things in common to bad as well as good men, and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes them with natural endowments and abilities to accompliſh thoſe ends that he looks at in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; And ſince bad men are often poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97026:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> of them by juſt and lawful means, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing either in Divine or Humane Laws, to infringe their titles, but enough in both to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them; And ſince 'tis impoſſible without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation to know aſſuredly who has grace, and who has not; And ſince bad men have juſt right, and lawful authority to alienate what they have, and to veſt others in it: ſure he has need of a ſtrong Faith, that can believe Hereſie, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or any other ſin, doth null any man's title to his worldly eſtate. But Pride makes men think they have a right to all things; and therefore they are troubled to ſee any body elſe poſſeſſed of them. Hence the Apoſtle telleth us, <hi>Envy cometh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>of pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Another cauſe of Envy, is Covetouſneſs. For if I did not deſire my Neighbours Eſtate; I ſhould not envy him the injoyment of it. We do not grieve at the abſence of that, the preſence of which we never wiſhed for. Where love and deſire go not before, grief never follows after. The degree of Envy is often anſwerable to the degree of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs. And therefore as none were more cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, ſo none were more envious than the <hi>Phariſees.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>That the love of money is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>root of all evil,</hi> and therefore of this of Envy: Which he ſeems not very obſcurely to inſinuate, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That while ſome coveted after i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, they pierced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves through with many ſorrows.</hi> Grief and Sorrow being ever the concomitants of Envy.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97026:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> 5. Uncharitableneſs is another cauſe of Envy. For he that loves his Brother will not grudge, but rather rejoice at any good that happens unto him. This the Apoſtle aſſerts, telling us, <hi>That Charity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>not.</hi> Where there's leaſt of charity, there's moſt of Envy. And the Devil who is moſt unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, is the moſt envious; alwaies grieving at any good that happens to man, and indeavouring by all arts and devices imaginable, to deprive him of it, and by all means to bring upon him all the evil he can. Doubtleſs if God did not hold him back, and limit his power, he'd ſoon deſtroy this lower World, as envying thoſe wicked mens any longer reprieve from the extreameſt miſery that inhabit it: And for fear that, by all the means and methods of Gods Providence that he uſes to that end, they ſhould at laſt be brought to repentance. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that requeſt mentioned in the Goſpel, where the rich Glutton in Hell is repreſented as petitioning <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 27. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he would ſend <hi>Lazarus</hi> to his Father's houſe, unto his five Brethren, that he might tell them what was befallen him, and what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them to do in order to their being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, <hi>leſt when they died, they ſhould come to the ſame place of torment,</hi> where he was, did not proceed from charity to his Brethren, there being nothing ſo love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt the damned; But from fear, leſt they to whom he had given evil example, and with whom he was a Companion in all Vice and Wickedneſs, ſhould enhance his miſery, and add to his torment, when they were once come where he was.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97026:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 6. Idleneſs is another cauſe of Envy. For when men are grown poor by ſloth, they begin to envy thoſe who are grown rich by their induſtry. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tells us, <hi>That the ſoul of the ſluggard deſireth, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>hath nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he has by ſloth and negligence waſted and ſpent his own, he then deſires, and envies his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's eſtate. An idle perſon is commonly envious, and would be glad if ſome great misfortune might happen to his Neighbour's eſtate, though he himſelf was never the better for it. So near approaches does the envious perſon make toward Hell even in this life.</p>
            <p>Thus if we look upon Envy either in its Nature, or in its Cauſes, we muſt needs ſee enough to make us abhorr it as a moſt deteſtable vice. Neither will it appear otherwiſe, if we view it in its effects, ſince the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Where envying is, there is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">James 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>every evil work.</hi> Now thoſe effects I ſhall rank into three Heads, becauſe ſome reſpect God, ſome other men, and ſome the envious perſon himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Some reſpect God, who is ſtruck at by all ſin, but has contempt offered him by this ſin of Envy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For he that envies his Brother any good that he poſſeſſes, does in effect find fault with God, as if he had not done well in ſo diſpoſing of it. The elder Brother in the Parable, who was troubled to ſee the proviſion made for his younger Brother's entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97026:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereby blamed his Father who cauſed it. Such an interpretation our Saviour makes of their grutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at thoſe on whom the Maſter beſtowed a daies wages when they wrought but an hour, ſaying, <hi>Is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 20. 15.</note> 
               <hi>it not lawful for me to do what I will with my own?</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that whoever he be, that's troubled at any good which another injoys, does thereby find fault with him that beſtowed it upon him. And what are we that we ſhould inſtruct God, or blame him for his diſpoſals? As if without us he knew not how rightly to beſtow his benefits. Which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries blaſphemy with it, it being a charging God with want of wiſdom, and the fetting our ſelves above him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He that envies his Brother any good that he poſſeſſes, does in effect quarrel with the goodneſs of God, with that Attribute whereby he's propenſe and inclinable to do good to all his Creatures. If the envious man might have his mind, he'd limit and bound his Goodneſs, and confine all the offices of it wholly to himſelf, not liking, nor by any means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving that others ſhould be benefited by it. And ſo would have God ceaſe to be what he is, to pleaſe him. As if he were not infinitely Perfect, Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Deſirable, not only in reſpect to the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent excellency of his Nature; but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Munificence, Bounty, and Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Creatures. So that you ſee, the envious man would not only detract good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but alſo Goodneſs from God, which is the cauſe of all that good which his Neighbour is parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97026:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> 3. He that's troubled at any good that another poſſeſſes, goes about to eclipſe the glory of God. For every excellency, and every good that we ſee the creature endued with, iſſues from God. As all the light the Moon has, it borrows it of the Sun; ſo every good which the creature enjoys, is derived from God, and points at its original from whence it came. He therefore that envies any good that his Neighbour has, ſince 'tis a repreſentation of God, and an effect that manifeſts the cauſe from whence it ſprang, would darken and obſcure the glory of God. How can he be ſaid to deſire the glory of God, that's grieved to ſee it ſhine forth in its excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent luſtre, ſo as men might admire and adore it? As he cannot be ſaid to be a friend to a Prince's Honour who is troubled at every thing he does, whereby to obtain to himſelf, an eſteem from his people. Beſides, the envious perſon does as good as tell the World, that all the good which God does to others, is not worth his thanks: and ſo he does what in him lies, to hinder God from receiving that tribute of Praiſe that belongs unto him, and not only would withdraw from men the things that are theirs; but would withhold from God the things that are Gods.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He offers the greateſt affront, and diſcovers the greateſt enmity to God imaginable. For when a man is ſleighted the more for being regarded by us, and when the more kind we are to him, others ſtand at the greater diſtance from him, we account it argues their great ſleight and contempt of us. Now, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97026:12"/> more kind God is to any one, the more does the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious man hate him. If God has done well for him, the envious man preſently wiſhes him ill. The more he has of the expreſſions of God's, the leſs he ſhall be ſure to have of his love: And the more regard he ſeems to have from God, the leſs he ſhall have from him. For the more good he receives from the bountiful hand of Heaven, the thicker are the Arrows of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſhot at him. As <hi>Xenophon</hi> has obſerved in his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 157.</note> 
               <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how great an evil Envy is, if we conſider the effects of it, as they reſpect God. For it quarrels with his Wiſdom, grieves at his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, would detract from his glory, and deprive him of that Honour and Praiſe which belongs unto him, and is to be paid him by all his creatures, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the greateſt affront, and diſcovers the greateſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Thoſe effects of Envy which reſpect others, are alſo very evil.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As it makes a man curious to inquire into their concerns, and to pry into their ſecrets, that he may find out ſomething or other that he thinks diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es them. <hi>Plutarch</hi> has obſerved this to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 518.</note> of Envy, That 'tis curious in ſearching into the misfortunes and miſhaps of others, and 'tis dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to pick up all ſtories that ſeem to leſſen them. For ſince the envious man is troubled at any good which others enjoy, he's very ſolicitous to acquaint himſelf with ſome of their evils to eaſe his own mind,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97026:13"/> finding he cannot be at quiet in himſelf, ſo long as all things are well with them whom he envies. And therefore he takes all occaſions to inform himſelf of any evil accident that happens either to their Eſtates or Perſons, and that which is their intereſt to keep ſecret and hid, he'll uſe all the means he can to get to the knowledge of, that ſo he may have the better advantage to diminiſh and leſſen them in the eſteem of others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Envy cauſes a man to wiſh the hurt of thoſe whom he envies. For ſince he's troubled at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's good, he muſt needs wiſh his hurt, becauſe that would remove the ground of his trouble. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will any paſt obligations make him of a better mind; For he'll overlook all kindneſſes received. Nay, ſuch engagements as are founded in nature it ſelf, are not ſtrong enough to allay the diſtemper, as is apparent, in that the neareſt Allies are often ſtung with it, and diſcover it againſt one another, as did <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren againſt him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another effect of Envy is, The rejoycing at any evil that befalls the envied party, contrary to charity or love, which <hi>rejoiceth not in iniquity,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 6.</note> but rather cauſes a man to grieve when any evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls his Brother, of what kind ſoever it be. The envious man quite inverts the order of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 15. <hi>For he weeps with them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, and rejoices with them that weep.</hi> A temper ſo far from being Chriſtian, that there's nothing of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in it, but very much of the Devil. For if there be any thing that may be called joy in Hell, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97026:13"/>
'tis at the ſin and miſery of others whom they'd draw into the ſame condemnation with themſelves. And yet there are but too many that would be not only accounted Chriſtians, but would be alſo thought to be in the higheſt form amongſt thoſe that are called ſuch, who imitate in this, thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits, who delight in nothing more, than in publiſhing the ſins and failings of their Brethren, eſpecially of their Superiours. Hence they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt alwaies, and in all companies, declaiming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Magiſtrates and Miniſters, and diverting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with telling ſtories of their ſuppoſed miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages; whereas, if they did not envy their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Revenues, they would be contented to let them paſs without their Cenſure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another effect of Envy is, the endeavouring to do the envied party an ill turn: And to be ſure, ſince an envious man deſires another's ill, he'll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it what he can. And this is done,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By meditating his hurt, or projecting in his mind how to bring it to paſs. Thus when <hi>Saul</hi>'s Envy was once ſtirred up againſt <hi>David,</hi> he thought of nothing but his ruine, and was alwaies plotting means to bring his purpoſe about. He had an evil eye upon him ever after that he heard the Women <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 9.</note> in their Song aſcribed unto <hi>David,</hi> more than unto himſelf. Sometimes he deſigns to kill him with a Javelin; another time he thinks the beſt means he can uſe to effect his purpoſe, is the giving him his Daughter <hi>Michal</hi> to Wife, <hi>that ſhe may be a ſnare unto him:</hi> Sometime he thinks to entrap him by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97026:14"/> ſecret fraud; at other times, to aſſault him by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen violence. And as <hi>David</hi>'s fame encreaſed by his worthy Deeds, ſo did <hi>Saul</hi>'s envy towards him. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 29, 30. and Ch. 19. 1.</note> And therefore he was ever caſting about how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him.</p>
            <p>But we need not have had recourſe to ancient times, for proof that envy cauſes men to meditate the hurt of thoſe whom they envy, ſince our own will furniſh us with too many inſtances of ſuch, whoſe heads are alwaies working how the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to miſchief thoſe whom they are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſee in ſuch proſperity, who are reſtleſs not only to ruine ſingle perſons, but whole orders of men amongſt us, to the apparent wrong, or rather the ſubverſion of both Church and State; who are ſo ſtark mad with Envy and malice, that ſo they might but pull down the houſe where thoſe whom their fancies have created their enemies, do inhabit, could be content themſelves to periſh in the ruins of it with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another means whereby the envious perſon endeavours to do others an ill turn, is by detraction. And therefore the Apoſtle has very fitly joined theſe two together, Envies and all evil Speakings; <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 1.</note> becauſe one is the Cauſe, the other is the Effect. Envy leſſens others what it can: It will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to have ſo much of any thing as really they have, that makes them appear conſiderable in the world. And they ſhall be ſure to have large additions, and greater degrees of that attributed to them, which ſeems any way to diminiſh them,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97026:14"/> than juſtly belongs to them. Hence amongſt thoſe who take their meaſures of a man's worth, by his riches; that is, amongſt the ſillier ſort of people, who know no better; the envious man will take great pains, and uſe many arguments to perſuade that thoſe whom he envies, are thought much weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier than they are. Amongſt thoſe that are taken with Beauty, he'll ſay, they are not at all handſome. If he meets with them that value a man for his Learning, he'll aſſure them that he never had any thing that might juſtly entitle him to it. If he be accounted wiſe, He'll tell them, the quite contrary is true of him. If he be eſteemed for his piety, that is ſo eminent and perſpicuous, that it cannot be hid, he'll bring in ſome But, or other, that ſhall ſhade and eclipſe it. Hence alſo every little imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Body ſhall be termed a deformity; and every misfortune that happens to him, ſhall be reckoned up, as ſo many inſtances of his own folly, as well as of Divine Vengeance againſt him. His common failings ſhall be heightned into vices, and becauſe he is not more than a man, envy will repreſent him to be worſe than a beaſt. Hence ſpring thoſe filthy Libels that are thrown about againſt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, whereby their faults are exaggerated, and foul reproaches caſt upon them, on purpoſe to make them deſpicable in the eyes of the people. If envy may be believed, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> God's Magiſtrate, and God's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, were proud, and took too much upon them, and every one of the Congregation were as good as <note place="margin">Numb. 16. 3.</note> they. But here indeed, <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> were more charitable and ingenuous than ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97026:15"/> who ſucceed them, in that they'd allow <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to be holy as well as themſelves, and did not wholly appropriate it to their own Party.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying violent hands, or offering open force againſt the envied party. This ſin of Envy was the cauſe of the firſt Murther in the World, I mean, that of <hi>Abel</hi>'s. And it has been a fruitful Mother of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſince. 'Twas that which cauſed our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's death; For the Prieſts <hi>delivered him for envy.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 27. 18. 18.</note> And ſome whoſe greateſt crimes were their Eſtates and Honours, have drunk of the ſame Cup in the memory of many of us, and therefore we may gueſs that Envy ſerved it up. So ſitly does the Apoſtle <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 21.</note> place murders after envyings. And indeed, Envy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver baniſhes love out of the heart, and is accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome degree of hatred. And he that hates his Brother is a murtherer, and is like to be proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt as ſuch at the great day, though he do not actually take away his life. For as the malicious intent or the deſigning and compaſſing the death of the Prince is Treaſon by our Law, and all overt Acts are looked upon only as evidences that manifeſt it; ſo the hating of our Brother in our hearts is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the laying violent hands on him, and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally killing him, only argues the murderous intent to men, who otherwiſe are not able to know certainly our hearts. But God wants none of theſe evidences, ſince he knows what is in man, and needs not the help of the Effects, to lead him to the knowledge of the Cauſe. Thus we ſee the effects of Envy as they reſpect others, or God and our Brethren, and from thence may underſtand the evil of it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97026:15"/> 3. But the truth is, The effects of Envy are moſt pernicious and deadly to the envious man himſelf. For God is not hurt by it. He that ſhoots an Arrow <note place="margin">Job 35. 6.</note> up to Heaven, is likely enough to have it fall upon his own pate; And ſince Envy is levelled againſt the good of our Brother, which God is the Author of, 'tis moſt likely he'll either ſecure him in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his own gift, or elſe make up the loſs of it to him ſome other way. Thus though the envy of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren prevailed ſo far, as to make him leave his own Country; yet God took care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <note place="margin">Act. 7. 9.</note> him in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court. Certainly the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon himſelf has the worſt of it, or is hurt moſt by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For it has a moſt pernicious effect both upon his body and mind, cauſing leanneſs and paleneſs to his Body. As the Poet has obſerved, <hi>He's ſick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor. Ep. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>his Brother's well, and the better 'tis with another, the worſe 'tis with him.</hi> As his Brother encreaſes in his Fortunes, in the ſame degree he decreaſes in his Comforts. For it creates great diſturbance, trouble, and grief to his mind. <hi>Solomon</hi> calls it, <hi>the rottenneſs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14. 30. <hi>Invidiâ Siculi non invenêre Tyranni Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus tormentum.</hi> ibid.</note> 
               <hi>of the bones.</hi> And the Satyriſt ſayes, <hi>'Tis a moſt fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting tormenting Diſeaſe, ſuch as will let the mind enjoy no quiet, that is infeſted with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By this means we are moſt likely to loſe the favour of men. For he that envies his Brother, will be apt at ſome time or other to detract from him, and ſpeak againſt him, and that will loſe him in the eſteem of thoſe that hear him. For they that are at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97026:16"/> preſent unconcerned in the envious man's detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will think with themſelves they know not how ſoon they may be ſo, ſince he may have the ſame Motives to ſpeak againſt them hereafter, as he has now to ſpeak againſt others. And hence they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conceive a very mean opinion of him, and that moſt deſervedly, becauſe they ſee him ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that's good in others. And therefore <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> compares Envy to the <hi>Cantharides,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Plut. de Invid.</hi>
               </note> the ripeſt Fruits, and fulleſt blown Roſes; 'tis levelled againſt the higheſt worth and greateſt good.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this means we certainly exclude our ſelves the favour of God; who cannot chooſe but be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with us for being troubled and grieved at his diſpoſals, and for loving them the leſs to whom he's moſt kind and bountiful. Beſides, envy is the Parent of many other evils, as you have heard, and ſo involves us in the greater guilt, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt needs render us the more hateful in the ſight of God. Since his love is proportioned to the degree of goodneſs which he beholds in men, ſo will his hate to the degree of evil.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This ſin of Envy will exclude a man Heaven, as well as any other. For proof of which, you need read only what's written <hi>(Gal.</hi> 5. 21.) Where the Apoſtle reckons envyings amongſt the <hi>works of the fleſh,</hi> and then adds; <hi>Of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Mere ſelf-love therefore, one would think, ſhould,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97026:16"/> if there wanted other Motives, prevail effectually with men to lay down this filthy paſſion, and to be as fearful of admitting it into their boſoms, as they would be of a Thief into their houſes, who comes to rob them of all that's valuable in them; And to be as careful of ſuppreſſing it, as they would be of fire, that (if it be let alone) would waſt and devour all before it.</p>
            <p>But beſides what has been ſaid already. I might add,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That 'tis a baſe Vice, as appears by every one's being aſhamed to own it. There being ſome that will own other ſins; but every one endeavours to hide this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis a Vice highly unjuſt, ſince 'tis ſo far from giving others their due, that it purſues them with the greateſt hatred, ſcorn, and reproach, who deſerve the beſt. Hence the Moraliſt tells us, <hi>That we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not envy any one juſtly.</hi> There may ſome ſeeming <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> juſtice appear in our hatred, becauſe the party may have done us an injury: But there can be none in our Envy, becauſe 'tis levelled againſt him that has done us none. And 'tis for his good, not for his evil, that he's envied. 'Tis true, in one ſenſe, it may be <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Orat. 27.</note> ſaid to be juſt (as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> has obſerved) becauſe 'tis a means to deſtroy him who foſters and cheriſhes ſo foul a Vice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis of a vaſt extent, and is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, bearing ill to all the fortunate and happy.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97026:17"/> Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that ingenious Moraliſt, before named, ſayes, <hi>'Tis a kind of infinite Thing, like an inflammation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in the Eye, that cauſes it to be diſturbed at every light it ſees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis moſt dangerous to them that are the objects of it. An envious man being a worſe enemy than he that's openly and profeſſedly ſo, becauſe an open enemy ſtrikes at us when our faces are towards him; but an envious man takes his advantages of doing us a miſchief when we are leaſt aware of him, skulking in ſecret, ſo that we cannot ward for our ſelves, which is moſt ingenerous in it ſelf, and moſt dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in its effects. For he wounds the ſoreſt, who is <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Greg. Naz. Orat. 32.</note> not thought to have any deſign of hurting us. And conſequently, it hurting the more, and being the more deadly, muſt needs be the more ſinful.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis a fooliſh Vice. For, beſides that the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon receives real damage by it in his body and mind, loſes the eſteem of men, and favour of God, which is ten thouſand times more valuable, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes himſelf Heaven: if he did rejoice at all the good that happens to another, he might certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſome gainer by it himſelf, ſince that very joy would be more advantagious to him, than the grief which the envious man has. And all thoſe goods that another is poſſeſſed of, might ſome way or other be to his profit; from his wiſdom he might have good counſel, from his piety, good example, from his Eſtate relief, if ever he ſhould come to want it. And many other waies one may be advantaged by the good which another is poſſeſſed of. Hence it is, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97026:17"/> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take away envy, and what I have is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tolle invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; tuum eſt quod babe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; Tolle invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp; meum eſt quod babes,</hi> in Pſal. 139.</note> 
               <hi>thine, and what thou haſt is mine.</hi> But the envious man loſes the benefit of all.</p>
            <p>And therefore having thus opened the nature of the diſeaſe, having taken an impartial view of it, both in its Cauſes, and in its Effects; charity requires, that I ſhould in the next place propoſe what's proper and ſovereign, in order to the remedy and cure of it. For I account when the Phyſician has faithfully and plainly demonſtrated the nature of the Malady, with the fatal and deadly conſequences of it, unleſs it be timely removed, He has done ſufficient to perſwade the Patient to make uſe of thoſe remedies which he ſhall rationally offer as proper to expel it.</p>
            <p>Now having already found out the Cauſes, 'tis but removing them, and the Cure will be effected.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Therefore, endeavour after a conviction of the vanity and emptineſs of all worldly goods. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we did not think them better than they are, we ſhould envy no man the poſſeſſion of them. If a man had as much of them as he deſired, he might ſtill be miſerable. When a man's going into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, 'tis but little eaſe to his mind to think how well he's provided for in this. They are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ruine of wicked men, and they are ſnares and temptations to them that are good. For one man that's profited, I am perſwaded that ten are hurt by them. Since therefore they are ſo hazardous in the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there's no reaſon we ſhould envy them that have them. <hi>David</hi> ſaw them that had moſt of them,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97026:18"/> 
               <hi>to ſtand in ſlippery places.</hi> Beſides, we know not how much care, ſolicitouſneſs, pains, attendance, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they coſt ſome of them, ſo as that we'd be loth to purchaſe them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us cheriſh Humility, and indeavour after a mean opinion of our ſelves; and then we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think much at any good that happens to another, and ſhall account our ſelves to have beyond our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert already. He that thinks meanly of himſelf, will conclude, that God deals graciouſly with him, in that he gives him any thing. If he thinks himſelf to be leſs than the leaſt of all God's mercies, the leaſt of his mercies will pleaſe him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Have a love for, and bear good will to all men, and think charitably of them, unleſs there be evident cauſe to the contrary. For he that loves his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour will not grieve, but be glad of any good that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens unto him. And if we bear him good will, and deſire his good, 'twill rejoice us to ſee it. And if we think charitably of him, we ſhall think he deſerves it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Study contentment. Conſider in how much better circumſtances you are, than many others who have deſerved as well, and that your condition what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, is ſuch as God accounts the beſt for you. This is neceſſary, For he that looks with murmuring and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng on his own condition, is apt to look with envy on other mens. And he that's pleaſed with his own condition, will never be troubled to ſee his Neighbour's better.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97026:18"/> 5. Endeavour after a firm aſſent to all that God has reyealed of himſelf to the World. He has told us, That he is moſt Wiſe, Powerful, and Gracious, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to do good to his Creatures: If we did believe him to be ſo, inſtead of envying what others enjoy, we ſhould approve of his diſpoſals to them, and ſue to him for what we want our ſelves, reſting our ſelves ſatisfied in what it is his pleaſure to do to us or with us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Be alwaies well imployed. This is the way of making us become the envy of others, and of raiſing us to ſuch a condition that we ſhall not have ſo great temptation to envy them. But <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will cloath a man with raggs;</hi> and then he's moſt likely to envy thoſe that go better clad. Idleneſs brings a man to want, and then he's ready to envy his Neighbour's plenty.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To all theſe let us add, our hearty and humble ſupplications to Almighty God, who is the giver of all good things, that he would endue us with ſuch a love to our Brethren, as will extirpate and root all envy out of our hearts; that he would ſo thoroughly convince us of the fading vanity of all worldly goods, that we may neither eagerly deſire them for our ſelves, nor be grieved when we ſee others enjoy them, having far better things in our eye, than this World can afford us. Let us beg of him a humble heart, that we may ever think our ſelves to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our deſert, may ſubmit our ſelves wholly to his diſpoſals, and may eſteem others better, and more deſerving than our ſelves, and in whatever ſtate we
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97026:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> are, we may be therewith content; Being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that as he's All-ſufficient, ſo whatever his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſees beſt for us, his Goodneſs will communicate to us, if we uſe our own ſincere endeavours, and are not wanting to our ſelves in the uſe of thoſe means which are neceſſary in order to thoſe ſupplies which we expect from his hands.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
